Harry Heffner Empire Ranch photograph collection circa 1875-1954
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections
Harry Heffner Empire Ranch photograph collection circa 1875-1954
MS 506
Heffner, Harry 1874-1965
Reminiscences, photographs, and photograph albums relating to the Empire Ranch between 1893 and 1905 including cattle and ranching activities. There are also typescript copies of letters written to Edward L. Vail, between 1875 and 1877, from Walter Vail and others.
2.25 linear feet
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections University of Arizona PO Box 210055 Tucson, AZ 85721-0055 Phone: 520-621-6423 Fax: 520-621-9733 URL: http://speccoll.library.arizona.edu/
Restrictions
There are no restrictions on this collection.
Biographical Note
Harry Heffner was employed by Walter Vail of Vail and Gates at the Empire Ranch, Pantano, Arizona from June 1893 to 1905. He started as a ranch hand, and later was manager of the ranch from 1902 to 1905. Heffner moved to California in 1905 where he owned various ranches, managed the Gates estate, and was director of various water districts. From 1939 to 1944, he was Vice President of the Cortaro Farms Company in Marana.
Arrangement
This collection is organized into two series
Series I: Biographical, histories, and reminiscences, ca. 1875-1954
Series II: Photographs and photograph albums ca. 1893-1905
Scope and Content Note
Primarily photographs but also a small amount of reminiscences, typescripts of letters, and notes concerning Harry Heffner’s involvement with the Empire Ranch from 1893 to 1905. There are typescript copies of letters written to Edward L. Vail, 1875 to 1877, mostly by Walter Vail, and there are original ranch and water documents from Heffner’s California activities, 1905-1937
There are photographs of ranch life, cattle and horses, and the McFadden family. Two large photograph albums, one with 102 photographs, the other with 101 photographs relating to Harry Heffner and the Empire Ranch operations, ca. 1893-1905. Images depict cattle and ranching activities including branding, ranch houses, wagons and automobiles (including an 8-team wagon and the “first Oldsmobile in Arizona, 1904”). There are images of Harry Heffner, H. V. McFadden, Bert Alvord, the Herbert Drachman family, the Vail family, and Jim Seaver. Also present are images of Crittenden ruins, Tucson buildings, and Gardner Ranch (Colossal Cave)
The photographs in the albums and other items have been digitized as part of the University of Arizona Institutional Repository and can be found under the Empire Ranch Collection;and an oral history interview with Harry Heffner by Charles U. Pickrell is located at AZ 21.
Access Terms
Heffner, Harry, 1874-1965
Vail, Walter L., 1852-1906--Correspondence.
McFadden family.
Ranch life—Arizona—Pictorial works.
Cattle—Arizona—Pictorial works
Empire Ranch (Ariz.)—Pictorial works.
Container List
- Series I: Biographical, histories and reminiscences 1875-1954
  This series is arranged topically
  - Biographical materials, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Heffner’s letters and reminiscences, 1936-1954 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Ranch and water documents, California, 1905-1937 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Typescript letters to Edward L. Vail, 1875-1877 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Series II: Photographs and photograph albums 1893-1905
  This series is arranged topically,
  - Harry Heffner, 1893-1905 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - People, 1893-1905 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Hadden McFadden family, 1896-1902 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Empire Ranch – Views, 1893-1905 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Empire Ranch buildings, 1893-1905 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Empire Ranch cattle and ranching, 1893-1905 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Empire Ranch horses, wagons, roads, 1893-1905 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Miscellaneous photographs, undated (Box 1, Folder 12)